Steve Niles

Senior Enterprise Software Developer

Toronto, Ontario, Canada steve.niles@gmail.com https://www.steveniles.dev

I am a life-long programmer with over a decade of professional experience working primarily on web-based enterprise software-as-a-service across multiple industries, from real estate management to precision agriculture, digital media distribution, and more.

I work full-stack, from back-end database and code to front-end functionality and design. My top priority is building systems that stand the test of time, focusing on quality, extensibility, and maintainability.

I'm not a "move fast and break things" developer; I prefer being part of a team that takes a more thoughtful and deliberate approach to architecture and implementation, aiming to avoid the most common pitfalls that deteriorate a software system's long-term health.

Tech Stack Highlights

Recent

- Web front and back end, libraries
- C# / .NET
- JavaScript, React, HTML, CSS
- SQL Server, MongoDB
- Git, Github

Previous

- Desktop applications (DOS & Windows)
- C++, Java, PHP, QBasic & Visual Basic
- AngularJS, jQuery
- Postgres
- Team Foundation Version Control

Recent Work Experience

As Full-Time Developer

- Method Customer Relationship Management Platform (2021-2023)
- Yangaroo Digital Media Distribution System (2019-2021)
- MRI Real Estate Software (2013-2019)

Responsibilities included recommending, architecting, implementing, and documenting new features, as well as maintaining existing ones; Creating and supporting unit and integration tests; Mentoring junior and intermediate developers

As Part-Time Teacher / Developer

- Niagara College First Year Object-Oriented Programming (2013)
- Niagara College Research & Innovation (2007-2013)

Roles included instructing students in GUI design and basic programming, as well as testing and grading student performance; Working on software research projects in partnership with local businesses; Personally presenting software projects at press conferences, trade shows, and to King Charles III, then Prince of Wales

Education

- Brock University Honours BSc in Computer Science (2013)
- Niagara College Computer Programmer Analyst Diploma (2009)

Favorite courses include Artificial Intelligence, Discrete Optimization, and Compiler Construction

Open Source

- Visual Studio / Dotnet Roslyn Found and fixed a bug in the static analysis code of Microsoft's .NET Compiler Platform
- MandelZoom Mandelbrot Set screensaver with technical guide on screensaver programming and GDI+ image processing techniques